Jesus Garcia Ramirez

jgarciaramirezai@gmail.com | +34665444632 | Leuven, Belgium | linkedin.com/in/jesusgarciaramirez

SUMMARY

Proactive machine learning engineer with 3+ years of specialized experience in creating and implementing effective ML solutions with a proven track record of excellent communication and teamwork demonstrated through successful collaboration within interdisciplinary teams of researchers, engineers and non technical stakeholders. Confident in the ability to excel in fast paced environments while supporting smart business decisions.

SKILLS

Technical Skills: Machine Learning Algorithms, CNNs, Time Series Analysis, Research, Data Visualization

Tools: Python (Pytorch, Skikit-Learn, SciPy, Pandas), MLOps, Microsoft Office, Slack Soft Skills: Effective communication, Knowledge sharing, Curiosity, Time management

Certificates: Introduction to Machine Learning in Production

EXPERIENCE

PhD Researcher, KU Leuven

Jan 2022 - Present

- Developed an accurate (80% explained variance) CNN-based model for predicting neuron responses to images, bridging the gap between **computational** and biological **vision**.
- Optimized Receptive Field estimation by designing a novel Gaussian approximation, reducing fitting parameters by thousands.
- Implemented a closed-loop pipeline leveraging CNN encoding models, successfully identifying optimal stimuli for recorded neurons within a high-pressure, one-day experiment.
- Created an end-to-end interactive visualization to enhance model interpretability and facilitate communication with non-technical stakeholders.

Research Engineer, KU Leuven

Jan 2021 - Dec 2021

- Engineered a highly accurate (92% success rate) and fast (microsecond inference) Brain Machine Interface system using a non-linear extension of Kalman filter, enabling real-time control for individuals with reduced mobility
- Developed an innovative **online retraining** procedure to reduce the amount of required training data resulting in a 90% data utilization reduction, paving the way for broader accessibility.
- Led a cross-functional team of researchers, engineers, and non-technical stakeholders to deliver the solution 6 months early, exceeding expectations.

PROJECTS

Efficient analysis of mobile eye tracker data using Deep Learning

- Developed an automatic labelling tool to streamline the analysis of mobile eye-tracking recordings from an art exhibition
- Finetuned a video classification model (SlowFast) using curated 10k sample dataset, reducing manual workload on 80% with 90% accuracy
- Adapted Resnet to handle multidimensional time-series data for behaviour prediction, achieving 60% automation with 80% accuracy

EDUCATION

PhD in Neuroscience,	Jan 2022 - Present
KU Leuven M.Sc. in Artificial Intelligence,	Sep 2019 - Sep 2020
KU Leuven B.Sc. Industrial Engineering,	Sep 2015 - Jul 2019
University of Seville	Sep 2013 - Jul 2019

ACHIEVEMENTS

Speaker at Society for Neurosciences in Washington D.C, USA	Nov 2023
• Presented poster: "Single neuron signatures of spatial attention in the human lateral occipital complex"	
Speaker at Neural Control of Movement in Victoria, Canada	Apr~2023
• Presented poster: "Comparing reach direction decoding in macaque PMv, PMd and M1"	
Speaker at Society for Neuroscience in San Diego, USA	Nov~2022
• Presented poster: "Single unit correlates of visual reasoning in the human lateral occipital complex"	

Speaker at Federation for European Neuroscience Societies in Paris, France

Jul 2022

Presented poster: "Object decoding with spatial attention in the human lateral occipital complex"

Speaker at Society for Neuroscience in Chicago, USA Nov 2021 • Presented poster: "Decoding reaching direction from macaque dorsal and ventral premotor and primary cortex"